# Barak Gila

■ barak.gila@gmail.com | 🖀 www.barakgila.com | 🛅 barakgila | 💆 @barakgila

Product- and business-minded software engineer, most experienced on the backend of a product team but comfortable working full-stack. I'm motivated by seeing how my work impacts users, by talking to them or analyzing data. I also love teaching and mentoring others. I value integrity, transparency, and ownership.

### Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Mos, Inc Remote

SOFTWARE ENGINEER April 2020 - March 2021

Mos uses software and human advisors to match college students with financial aid. Worked under the CTO as the only full-time engineer. Built functionality into the product end-to-end and also added infrastructure as needed.

Languages: Worked full-stack in Typescript and Javascript (Node.js, React/Redux).

**Technologies:** Serverless architecture on AWS Lambda, DynamoDB and Cloudwatch.

- · Designed and implemented an in-browser messaging system that replaced email/SMS between agents and users, using Quill.js.
- Implemented "pay later" payment option with payment reminder messages and retries.
- · Built user-facing aid list that allowed students to add grants and scholarships and track their progress.
- · Integrated the Surveymonkey API to track Net Promoter Score (NPS) at various stages in the user journey.
- Introduced industry best practices including postmortems, reusable scripts, and JSON-schema-enforced endpoints to the team.

Affirm, Inc San Francisco, California

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Jan 2017 - April 2020

Worked on Affirm's consumer-facing loan product, which lets users generate a virtual card in the app to use their loan anywhere. Collaborated with my team to build the underlying virtual card platform which powers more than 20% of Affirm loans.

Languages: Primarily worked on the Python backend (frameworks including Luigi, Celery, Flask) with some Javascript and React/Redux.

- Designed a new backend service to allow Affirm to approve or deny credit network transactions in real time (99.99% within 3s). Created a widely-used internal webapp, for example to restrict certain cards to a specific merchant.
  - The greater control over transactions was critical for Affirm to expand from ecommerce to enterprise merchants and physical stores.
- Scaled transaction processing logic as loan volume grew by more than 10x by increasing reliability and robustness.
- Conceived and led an initiative to give customers control over their card processing, such as requesting a refund when done with the card.

  This increased loan volume substantially and reduced customer service contacts by as much as 50% for impacted users.
- Developed a take-home interview completed by 1000+ candidates, which better predicted performance and saved interviewing hours.

LEAD, INCLUSION & RETENTION Feb 2018 - Dec 2018

- Led the Inclusion & Retention group at Affirm within the Diversity & Inclusion program.
- · Helped grow our Employee Resource Groups (ERGs) from 5 to 13 groups, and oversaw their budget.

## EECS Department, UC Berkeley Undergraduate Student Instructor

Berkeley, California

EECS Department, UC Berkeley

Aug 2015 - Dec 2016

- Served as three-time teaching assistant (TA) for CS 170, the upper-division algorithms course of 500 students.
- In fall 2016, served as head TA: I managed course logistics and helped hire TAs and readers.
- · Led discussion sections, designed course materials, and tutored students.

Airbnb San Francisco. California

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

May 2016 - Aug 2016

Built support for European bank transactions (SEPA) into the company's new payments service, which handled a fifth of host payouts.

### **Education**

#### **University of California, Berkeley**

Berkeley, California

B.S. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING AND COMPUTER SCIENCE

Aug 2013 - Dec 2016

- Coursework: Data Structures; Algorithms (undergrad and grad); Artificial Intelligence; Machine Learning
- Scholarships: Regents' Scholarship, Cal Alumni Organization's Leadership Award
- **GPA:** 3.9